בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we are getting close to the end here.
We pick up with the משנה Mishnah at today's דף Daf is
ל"ב, Lamed Bet, 32. We pick up with the משנה Mishnah on
the bottom of ל"א, Lamed Aleph, ל"ב. Lamed Bet. And we are
now talking, as we said, we have moved from talking about הקדש
Hekdesh and
the issues at the end of
בחוקותי Bechukotai and now we're in the יובל Yovel parts of בהר
Behar about the fields going back in simple areas of sale. So
we dealt with, so we're dealing now with selling, we dealt with
selling
שדה אחוזה Sdei Achuzah and now we're dealing with selling a house
in בתי ערי חומה Batei Arei Chomah where you have a year
to buy it back and otherwise goes completely over and you have
totally lost it, you don't even get it back at the יובל.
Yovel. So let's take a look.
And what happens at the end of the year because we just
had a discussion about how you count the year, solar year, lunar
year and so on. משנה: Mishnah: בראשונה, Barishonah, and this משנה Mishnah
is quoted in גיטין Gittin as well. בראשונה, Barishonah, and you'll see
why in a minute. בראשונה היה נטמן יום שנים עשר חודש. Barishonah
hayah nitman yom shneim asar chodesh. Originally the purchaser would hide on
the last day of the year because the seller would be working
to get the money together and presumably he would really work hard
as the year was ending. So the buyer would make himself scant
during the end of that year and particularly at the last day
because he doesn't want to be forced to sell it back. Okay,
so כדי שתחלוט לו, kedei shetechlot lo, so he should get it
permanently. התקין הלל, Hitkin Hillel, הלל Hillel established שיהא תולש מושב sheyehei
tolesh moshav or something תולש מוטב, tolesh motav, רש"י Rashi has חולש.
cholesh. Anyway, he would throw the money, לשכה, lishkah, that you can
just throw the money into the temple treasury, into like a room
in the temple or into a box in the temple. ויהא שובר
את הדלת ונכנס, Vehei shover et hadelet venichnas, and you could break
your way into the apartment and go in in order to emphasize
that you had seized it and possessed it.
Oh yeah, because it's your house now, you can break in.
It's your house, exactly. So presumably you didn't need to break in,
you just needed to give the money, but this would really be
to make it very clear that you had taken possession by the
right day.
And then comma,
אימתי שירצה, eimatai sheyirtzeh,
and go in whenever you want, meaning you don't, so apparently it
doesn't have to be that you break in on that day, but
the point is even if he resists and tries to lock you
out, once you've given in the money, you now can take it
even back even by force.
I'm sorry, I put the comma in the wrong place. ויהא שובר
את הדלת ונכנס, Vehei shover et hadelet venichnas, and you would break
the door and enter in, like I said originally, probably on the
day itself to emphasize that you had taken possession by the right
time. And then comma, אימתי שירצה הלז, eimatai sheyirtzeh halaz, and whenever
the other guy wants, יבוא ויטול את מעותיו, yavo veyitol et ma'otav,
let him come and collect his money. Okay, so you say, look,
I've given the money, it's there waiting for you, I'm taking possession,
you can't say oh I didn't get the money, it's there waiting,
you collect it whenever you want. Thank you very much. Of course,
it's a little bit of a problem that if you don't live
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, how exactly do you get to the לשכה lishkah
to deposit your funds, but I guess there's only so much that
you can do and you needed a central location. And therefore, if
it was really, you know, a concern, of course if you woke
up on the last day and couldn't find him and you can't
get to ירושלים Yerushalayim in time to deposit the funds, it's not
exactly sure what you could do. But anyway, this is one of
the תקנות takanot of הלל Hillel and this is quoted in גיטין
Gittin because in גיטין Gittin they collect a lot of תקנות מפני
תיקון העולם, takanot mipnei tikkun ha'olam, in particular תקנות takanot of הלל,
Hillel, which is the famous one is of course this and, this
isn't as famous as of course the real famous one, which is
about the פרוזבול, pruzbul, which is about שמיטה. shmitah. Now I wanted
to make a point about why this whole thing took effect because
maybe this is the question Charlie was meaning to ask, we'll get
to Charlie in a minute. But anyway, the question here is it
sounds like in הלל's Hillel day the laws of יובל Yovel applied,
right? Because he had to make a תקנה takanah in order for
this to apply. Now you would think on the face of it,
fine, it's also consistent with the idea that he made a תקנה
takanah by שמיטה, shmitah, right? And about פרוזבול pruzbul because the laws
of יובל Yovel applied, the laws of שמיטה shmitah applied, one and
the same. The only two problems: one problem is that according to
other גמרות, Gemaras, יובל Yovel only applies when all of the tribes
and most of the inhabitants are living in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
which certainly was not true in the period of the second בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Problem number one. Now maybe you would say there's
some debate about that, but it's not clear, it seems like that's
completely consensus. The other problem is that the גמרא Gemara in גיטין
Gittin says how was הלל Hillel do a פרוזבול pruzbul to make
a run-around around a תורה דין Torah din that you have to
annul the loans? Meaning this is one thing, this isn't a run-around,
this is a complete reinforcement of the תורה דין. Torah din. It's
ensuring that the seller has the right until the very last day.
You are trying to do a run-around, you the buyer, by hiding
and avoiding. הלל Hillel is making just sure that this guy still
has the right, that somehow בית דין Beis Din will collect the
money for the buyer, represent the buyer in order to ensure, or
for the seller, excuse me, in order to represent, in order to
protect the rights for the buyer. But how could he do פרוזבול,
pruzbul, isn't that a complete run-around? So the גמרא's Gemara answer is,
and even if technically it works for whatever
the
reason פרוזבול pruzbul works and this is not the פרוזבול *Pruzbul*. And
the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* answer is, well, because in Hillel's day, the laws
of annulment of the loans no longer applied because שמיטה shmitta *Shmita*
didn't apply. Okay, I'm not going to go into the details, but
that's the basic thrust of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So now we've
got a problem. On the one hand, this sounds like even יובל
yovel *Yovel* applied, right? And the other hand, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says,
and that doesn't logically fit with what we know about the normal
criteria of יובל yovel. *Yovel*. On the other hand, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says that even שמיטה shmitta *Shmita* was only rabbinic at the
time of Hillel, which is how he was able to do his
תקנה takana *takkana*. So how do you reconcile this? So you could
say that יובל yovel *Yovel* was נוהג *noheg* just like שמיטה *Shmita*
was נוהג *noheg* at a rabbinic level. And it was all rabbinic,
it's true it wasn't biblical at the time of Hillel, it was
all rabbinic, but because but it was still נוהג *noheg* rabbinically, and
that's how he made his תקנה takana *takkana* within that context. תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos* here tries to argue the opposite, that actually not only
was שמיטה *Shmita* נוהג *noheg* biblically at the time of Hillel, but
even יובל yovel. *Yovel* was נוהג *noheg* biblically. What do you do
about the fact that you needed all the tribes in the land
in order for יובל yovel *Yovel* to be נוהג *noheg*? So if
you take a look at the end of this תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*
on ל"ב ע"א *lamed-bet amud-alef*, he says like this, he says,
it's like you see where the words שיטה מקובצת *Shita Mekubetzes* appears
and the on ל"ב ע"א *lamed-bet amud-alef*, like the just the header
there on the far left? So go across from that in תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos* where it says וצריך לומר *v'tzarich lomar*. So he says
like this, וצריך לומר דעל כרחך דאינך הכי נמי דנהגו יובלות בבית
שני *v'tzarich lomar d'al korchacha d'ein hachi nami d'nahagu yovlos b'bayis sheini*.
Yeah, really יובל Yovel *Yovel* was נוהג *noheg* on בית Bayis. שני
*Bayis Sheini*. ואף על גב דכל ישראל Yisrael. לא lo חזרו בימי
עזרא Ezra, *v'af al gav d'kol Yisrael lo chazru b'yimei Ezra*, even
though we know there was only a very small number of Jews
that went back at the time of עזרא Ezra *Ezra*, דכתיב Dechtiv
כל הקהל kol hakkahal כאחד ארבע רבוא אלפים שלש מאות וששים וששה
*d'ksiv kol hakahal k'echad arba ribo alafim shlosh meios v'shishim v'shisha*, to
quote the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* that says they were only like 40,000
odd people. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will quote that later. So how
could you say there was יובל Yovel. *Yovel*? You don't have most
of the inhabitants on the land. ומיהו מכל שבט ושבט חזרו מקצתן
*u'mihu mikol shevet v'shevet chazru miktazan*. There was a representative of all
of the שבטים *shevatim*, which is very strange because we assume that
by the time, you know, of the after after סנחריב *Sancheriv* and
so on, at most there was יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda*, you know, there
was לוי *Levi*, בנימין Binyamin. *Binyamin*, there was like two and a
half tribes, whatever it was, three tribes at most. So he says,
no, there were representatives of all the tribes. And I guess they
were all living in their tribal lands, because the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
has to say that they have to be separated in their tribal
lands, which is also bizarre because they were only living, you know,
at the time of the בית bayis שני *Bayis Sheini* only in
that small swath of יהודה Yehuda, *Yehuda*. They weren't inhabiting the whole
thing. ומיהו מכל שבט חזרו מקצתן והוי שפיר כמו כל יושביה עליה
*u'mihu mikol shevet chazru miktazan v'havei shapir k'mo kol yoshveha aleha*. Okay,
אף על גב דלא חזרו כולם *af al gav d'lo chazru kulam*.
So it really represents a obviously that's very strange. The רמב"ן *Ramban*
in his proofs against תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, you know, in the middle
of all his of all his other sort of textual proofs, just
has this sort of like a, you know, almost like a like
an intuitive or deep sort of, you know, sort of like logic,
you know, emotional response. And the רמב"ן *Ramban* says, how can you
say that they were נוהג *noheg* שילוח עבדים *shiluach avadim*? It says
והם עבדים לעבדים *v'heim avadim l'avadim*, meaning it's meaning there they were,
they themselves, you know, they themselves were subject to the rule of
the Persian government, you know, they didn't have any self-dominion. And how
can you say that, you know, can you imagine that they were
נוהג יובל *noheg Yovel*, which is something that fundamentally is about, besides
the technical criteria, is about being like,
you know, having your own dominion, having what's the word I'm looking
for? Sovereignty. Exactly. Thank you. So anyway, so the simple sense, of
course, based on all the criteria and just the historical reality, is
that there was no יובל *Yovel*. So the question still is then
what was Hillel's תקנה takana *takkana*? Was it a hypothetical תקנה takana
*takkana*? Was there maybe a rabbinic practice of יובל *Yovel*? It's not
exactly clear. Okay, but that is interesting that here it sounds like
יובל *Yovel* was נוהג *noheg* and the all the evidence is against
that. Charlie, you have a question?
Yeah,
don't you need more than just getting money to transfer property?
Well, you can force the sale. That's the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of
the תורה Torah *Torah*. So right, the חידוש *chiddush* of the תורה
Torah *Torah* is that I can buy it back from you the
whole year even if you don't want. Now the question the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* is going to say is, what does it mean to
force the sale? Let's say you're not hiding, let's say you're in
front of me. Is it like serving a what's it called? Process.
Process, what's it called? Not a warrant. What's it so what are
you trying to get? Subpoena. It's like serving a subpoena, but I
just have to throw it at you, meaning assuming you're here without
the תקנה takana *takkana* of Hillel. But you don't want to, but
I can force you to. How do I what defines that transaction,
you know, when it can be forced upon you? Now we actually
do have a little bit of a model for that, which is
called a גט get *get*, where you can serve a גט get,
*get*, you know, give a גט get *get*, man give גט get
*get* to his wife before the תקנה takana *takkana* of רבינו גרשום
*Rabbeinu Gershom*, even if she doesn't want. So somehow it has to
be put in her physical possession even if she even if she
wants even if she's trying to refuse it. So, you know, but
that's the question the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to address itself
to, but presumably that's if you're physically present. What if you're not
physically present? And
to stand in for the guy, right? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
never fully unpacks that, how this תקנה takana *takana* works. But as
I said, part of the question is, are is he dealing with
a biblical יובל *Yovel* or not? Presumably not. Okay, let's take a
look now at the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. אמר רבא amar Rava, *Amar
Rava*, said רבא Rava *Rava*, מתקנתו של הלל mi-takanaso shel Hillel, *mitakanaso
shel Hillel*, from הלל's *Hillel's* תקנה *takana*, we can infer the following
law, meaning what law can we infer? Not the תקנה *takana* itself,
but something implicit in the תקנה *takana*. If somebody says to his
wife, הרי זה גיטך על מנת שתתני לי מאתים זוז zuz, *harei
zeh gittech al menas shetitni li masayim zuz*, here's your גט get
*get* on the condition you give me 200 זוז *zuz*. So now
we're not talking about giving the גט get בעל כרחך *get b'al
korchach* that we already know. We're talking about now he doesn't want
to accept the 200 זוז *zuz*. She wants to give him the
200 זוז *zuz* and the גט get, *get* to be effective. He's
now trying to refuse it. Is or can you give that money
against the person's will? Is that considered a giving of the money?
He changed his mind.
What? Yeah, he changed his mind, right? ונתנה לו ve-nasna lo, *venasna
lo*, and she gave him the money, מדעתו מגורשת *mida'ato megureshes*, if
he willingly accepts the money it works, ובעל כרחו אינה מגורשת *u'v'al
korcho einah megureshes*, against his will not, that you can't force, that
a forced giving is not giving. How do you know? Let's take
a look, top of ל"ב עמוד א' alef. *lamed beis amud aleph*.
מדאיצטריך ליה להלל לתיקוני נתינה בעל כרחו הוי נתינה *mide'itztrich lei le'Hillel
letikunei netina b'al korcho havei netina*. He understands that הלל's *Hillel's* תקנה
*takana* was not just or primarily to address the case of the
guy not physically being present. It was to address the case of
the guy not wanting to accept it. And that his basic תקנה
*takana* was that even if he tried to refuse, we'll treat it
as though you accepted it. That's how we understand הלל's *Hillel's* תקנה
*takana*. Obviously that can be critiqued, which the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* will.
Can you explain that again? He wants the silver money back?
Yeah, essentially, essentially. It could be any number, he happened to choose
200.
And she has to pay it to her?
Yeah, so he pays her the כתובה *kesubah*, that's an outstanding debt.
But you can make a גט get. *get* on a condition, the
condition could be anything you want.
You can make a conditional גט get *get*.
According to הלכה halacha *halacha* you can. Nowadays the בית bayis דין
*beis din* won't allow it. But according to הלכה halacha? *halacha* you
can say, you can say...
And the fact that, but the fact that they choose the כתובה
*kesubah*, the 200 זוז
*zuz* is probably trying to reflect, right, his desire to get that
money back, that's true.
Or to not pay. Right.
No, but he has to pay, but he pays the debt, that's
a debt, but now for the in order for the גט get.
*get* to be חל *chal*, she has to pay him, do what
his condition. He could make a million conditions. He could say here's
your גט get *get* on the condition that you dance a jig.
Here's your גט *get* on the condition that you give me a
million dollars, that you give me two dollars, right? When you in
מסכת גיטין *Masechet Gittin* it's filled with these cases about conditional גט
*get*. We don't allow it nowadays. Okay, but in the in the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* it's filled with those cases and you're right, it
probably is using the example of 200 because he's trying to at
least, you know, negate
the effect of paying the כתובה *kesubah*. He's selling the גט *get*.
He's making her purchase. Right.
He is making her purchase. Right. I mean he's not framing it...
Right, exactly, exactly. Right, right, which is interesting because while the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara*, you're absolutely correct, because while the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has
cases about conditions, it's you know, and maybe here's a case where
it's trying to have him at least, you know, negate the effect
of paying the כתובה *kesubah*, it doesn't have the extreme cases of
extortion that we deal with nowadays. Okay, this is a small case
of that, not an extreme case of that. But you are correct.
It is extortion, right. Yeah. Yep. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, anyway, the point is, is the paying of money, can
it be done when you have to when you have to pay
to to fulfill a condition, can that be done against your will?
And he understands that the general rule is no, because he understands
that הלל's *Hillel's* תקנה *takana* was not so much about the guy
not being present, his basic תקנה *takana* was to make it work
even against the guy's will. Which means the general rule is that
it doesn't work against somebody's will. מדאיצטריך ליה להלל לתיקוני נתינה בעל
כרחו הוי נתינה *mide'itztrich lei le'Hillel letikunei netina b'al korcho havei netina*,
since הלל's *Hillel's* תקנה *takana* was that a giving something against somebody's
will is considered a giving, דבעלמא *de'be'alma*, the normal rule would be
נתינה בעל כרחו לא lo, הוי נתינה *netina b'al korcho lo havei
netina*, it wouldn't work. Because he understands that that was הלל's *Hillel's*
חידוש *chiddush*, that a forced that a giving against the will counts,
which means the general rule is it doesn't count. So ואותיב ליה
רב פפא ואי תימא רב אשי Rav Ashi רב שימי בר אשי
*v'osiv lei Rav Pappa v'isayma Rav Ashi Rav Shimi bar Ashi*, who's
they asked, who said that was הלל's *Hillel's* תקנה *takana*? ודילמא כי
איצטריך ליה להלל לתיקוני שלא בפניו *vedilma ki itztrich lei le'Hillel letikunei
shelo befanav*. No, no, no, you got it wrong. The basic תקנה
*takana* as it sounds like was that the guy wasn't present. Okay,
אבל בפניו aval befanav, *aval befanav*, if you're giving it in the
presence of the person, בין מדעתו בין בעל כרחו *bein mida'ato bein
b'al korcho*, whether it's willing or unwilling, הוי מתנה havei matana. *havei
matana* or הוי נתינה *havei netina*, it counts as a giving, right?
Because if all it's because if all the point was was that
you could just refuse, why do people go hiding? Just refuse. So
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* addresses that question. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says, well, you
know, if you're physically present, you know, there'll be pressure applied to
you to accept it. So it's a lot easier to just make
yourself scarce. Okay, so the fact it is true that people would
make themselves scarce, but he understood that the real it really would
have been sufficient just to refuse. I mean you make yourself scarce
because you don't want to be pressured to accept it. And the
response back was no, maybe that if you refused it, it would
have not it would have been completely ineffective. And even against your
will the guy could have given you the money, but that's why
you really had to make yourself scarce because you had to be
complete because because once you were present, then... And even against your
will it would have worked. Okay.
But it's not like the גט anyway. It's not analogous.
I understand. So I'm going to discuss the analogy. I'll discuss the
analogy in a minute. Let's finish that and then I'm going to
go, there's a big תוספות Tosafot that discusses the analogy, so I'm
going to get back to that. Okay, so let's take a look.
So he says, טאקע, taka, the against your will would have worked.
The reason you made yourself scarce was that, was that exactly that,
because since against your will would have worked, you had to get
out of there. So,
הוי מתנה. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some say that the discussion happened
in the reverse or whatever.
אמר amar, רבא, so said Rava, מתקנתו של הלל, הרי זה גט
על מנת שתתני לי מאתים זוז. harei zeh get al menas she-titni
li masayim zuz. From Hillel's תקנה we can infer that if somebody
says, "Here's your גט if you give me 200 זוז," ונתנה לו,
lo and she gave it to him, בין מדעתו בין בעל כרחו
הוי נתינה, bein mida'ato bein be'al korcho havei nesina, that even against
his will it works, that giving somebody something against their will does
work. How do you know that?
והוצרך לו הלל תקנה שלא בפניו, ve-hutzrach lo Hillel takana shelo befanav,
because Hillel's whole תקנה which addressed the case that the guy wasn't
around. אבל בפניו, he didn't need a תקנה if the guy was
around. Why? בין מדעתו בין בעל כרחו הוי נתינה, bein mida'ato bein
be'al korcho havei nesina, because it sounds like it would have worked
even against your will. So this is Rava starts from the opposite
end. He starts by assuming that against your will works, and that's
why the only case that wasn't covered was that the case where
the guy went into hiding.
מתקיף לה רב פפא ואיתימא רב שימי בר אשי, maskif lah Rav
Pappa ve-isima Rav Shimi bar Ashi, they ask him, how do you
know? ודילמא בין בפניו בין שלא בפניו מדעתו אין בעל כרחו לא,
ve-dilma bein befanav bein shelo befanav mida'ato in be'al korcho lo,
maybe it never would have worked against the guy's will, and maybe
the guy just went into hiding so he wouldn't be pressured to
accept it. But maybe the real issue was that the guy was
refusing it. והלל מאי דאיצטריך ליה תקין, ve-Hillel mai d'itztrich leh takin,
and Hillel made a תקנה because the one case that the guys
were getting around of it, they were avoiding pressure, they were avoiding
everything, is they were running away. But the real concern was not
just, or it wasn't just that he wasn't physically present, it was
also that it was against his will. And Hillel's תקנה had to
address two problems: number one, he wasn't physically present; number two, it
was against his will. Okay, so we don't know what the answer
is. Clearly the simple sense is that, you know, if the תורה
Torah says, by the way, that you can force the sale back,
then presumably that means that even against the person's will. So it
sounds like the real need for Hillel's תקנה was for the case
where the guy not being present. But the גמרא Gemara is saying,
no, maybe actually, you know, the תורה Torah demands that you accept
the money, but maybe you can refuse to accept it, and if
you refused it wouldn't work. So you're violating the תורה's Torah. demand
that you accept the money, but maybe actually it doesn't work against
your will, and Hillel's תקנה was coming to address that case as
well. And that similarly leaves open this question about the condition by
the גט, whether if it's done against the person's will, will it
work? Now the question is, going back to Rivka's issue, what is
the basis of comparison? As תוספות Tosafot says, you know, we never
say that you can gift something to somebody against their will. Right?
If I try to give Charlie my, I mean, I can't, זכין
לאדם שלא בפניו.
zachin l'adam shelo befanav.
That is in because we can assume the person wants it. But
let's say, right, let's say I have this junker of a car,
and if they don't want it?
No, no, no. Rivka, we will talk about the, it's true, there
are cases in the גט where there,
even if, yes.
Okay, let me lay out the principles and then we can debate
those cases because what you're dealing with is like two degrees removed.
Okay, but the base principle is, I have this junker of a
car, whatever, even if it's not a junker of a car, it's
a nice new car, but Charlie here has nowhere to park it
because he lives in Manhattan, there's nowhere to park, and I want
to give it to Charlie. And I say, "Here, here's the car,"
and I drive it into his driveway. If he says, "I don't
want to receive it," he doesn't own the car now, he doesn't
own it against his will. Now Rivka says, "One minute, we have
the principle זכין לאדם שלא בפניו." zachin l'adam shelo befanav. So why
doesn't Rivka take possession of the car for Charlie? Now normally that
would work because we assume that people want things for free. And
therefore the general assumption is that he wants it. But if Charlie
is yelling and screaming, "I absolutely do not want to take that
car," Rivka cannot take possession of it for him against Charlie's will.
Now there is interesting questions about what happens, can we ever sort
of say, ignore what Charlie is saying and say deep down he
really does want it, it is in his best interest? Some of
those issues come up in certain גט cases, which is I assume
what you're referring to.
Exactly, there is a גט and I know
of a number of
cases where this has been done to where a woman does not
want to accept the גט and they figure out some way, they'll
accuse her for example of being, of sleeping with another, she's committing
adultery. Right. And therefore it's a זכות zechut for her to be
divorced so she's no longer sinning. So I know cases.
Right, and you're absolutely right. They have cases like that about גט
זיכוי get zikuy
where they compel, the woman does not
want to accept
the גט, doesn't matter, she has a גט.
Right. So you are correct, there are cases about that.
Specifically in the case she doesn't want it.
I get it. I get it. So there are cases and you
learned earlier in ערכין, Arachin, for example, you know, cases like where
כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני, kofin oso ad she-yomar rotzeh ani,
you know, times where someone, I mean the man. So basically there
are cases where we will say that even if the person is
refusing, we can, we will claim that their refusal is נארשקייט narishkeit
and it still remains in their best interest and it still takes
effect. But those are very loaded cases. If it's a general case
where it's just questions about, you know, not sort of like religious
status and so on, just a question about. Should Charlie have to
deal with my car? Then we treat Charlie's refusal seriously and you
cannot take possession of it against his will. The reason the גט
is different is we make the claim, we can discuss this and
debate this and so on, but the claim there is is that
her refusal is נארישקייט narishkeit in the face of the sins that
she'll be doing and it still remains in her best interest and
so on. Okay, we would not say that if it was a
simple issue of like just a monetary transaction. So the general principle
is you somebody cannot take possession of something against their will. So
תוספות Tosafot, says, so what's this whole discussion about נתינה בעל כורחה?
netina b'al korcha? And תוספות Tosafot says it's not everything happens in
a vacuum like, oh, have my car. No, I don't want it.
Things can sometimes are things that for example, תוספות Tosafot gives a
couple of examples. I owe Charlie a hundred dollars. Charlie doesn't want
to take the money for whatever reason. It's not in his interest
to take it right now. Who knows why? I mean there's that
old joke by the way that you know two guys are sitting
on a subway and somebody comes on and says like with a
gun, you know, says like, okay, give me all your wallets. So
one guy turns to the other, oh Fred, here's the 20 bucks
I owe you.
So anyway, so sometimes you don't want to accept the money anyway.
Can I pay Charlie back now even though he doesn't want to
take the money? Okay, not on the subway. Okay, can you know,
is that good? Or you know, so there are questions where where
you know because Charlie let's say who knows, you know, let's say
we're out in the middle of nowhere, we're not going to get
into a bank for the next you know for the next 10
miles or whatever or three days. Charlie doesn't want to be holding
on to the money for the next three days. Can I still
say it? I owe you the money, take it back. I'm you
know I'm not responsible for it anymore. And so there are cases
where he's in a position where where I'm supposed to be giving
it back the money, I'm entitled to give him back the money,
it releases me of an obligation and so on where we might
say he doesn't really have a say in whether or not he
wants it or not. As soon as I put it in his
possession, I've done my duty. Okay, and that is sort of the
question here. I'm supposed I have a right to buy it back.
We might not say that means that he's halachically forced to accept
it. We might actually say since I'm entitled and have that right,
I've done my duty and it takes effect as soon as I
put it in his possession. And similarly is the question by the
condition of the גט. Now there, the woman has been given a
גט and she has been basically said you have the right or
you have the ability to make it effective by giving me 200
dollars. So since basically that's now he's entitled to do that and
it's under her control to make it effective giving that money, so
maybe she's able the definition of what it means to give that
money does not mean that the person has to willingly take possession,
just has to physically give. Okay, so that is you know the
basis of the analogy when you're not dealing with something in a
vacuum like, oh, I want to give this to you but you
have to want to accept it. But actually it's more sense of
like I'm executing my duty, I'm releasing myself from responsibility, I'm executing
my right. Those are cases where you might be able to do
it even if the other person doesn't want to but you just
physically put it in their possession. And that's the question that the
גמרא Gemara is asking. Okay, without a clear resolution. Yes.
In this example of the house, why are we even taking into
consideration that the person who purchased it doesn't want to accept it?
I mean why does No, it's in scenarios where you don't. Normally
if you're buying something you don't want to live in a place
for a year and then move out.
No, but I mean he bought it with that condition, right? I
mean he knew that that Right. I understand. Right.
Because you hope people don't necessarily you didn't have a say in
that and you hope people won't exercise their rights. Meaning is it
possible that you're willing to do it and then you got a
free year's rent which is what the גמרא Gemara said back you
got your money back. Sure it's possible, then you wouldn't go hiding.
But there are plenty of scenarios where you don't where you want
to keep your house, you know, so we're dealing with those cases.
What? I'm sorry.
Could be. Sure, there are places where you could say look I'll
be here, worst case scenario is I'll get all my money back
and I'll live here for a year free and maybe it'll just
keep on rolling it over, get a lot of free rent. Sure
there are those scenarios and then he won't go hiding. But there
are other scenarios where you want to keep it. Property value skyrocketed,
I just don't want to you know have to deal with a
move all over again. Who knows what the case is. Okay, we're
not saying every case was this way but we're saying enough were.
All right, so anyway, so let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says let me just look one more second and תוספות Tosafot
give one or two examples from the תוספות Tosafot because I think
I forgot one or two. Hold on. חובה ליתן, chova liten, right,
returning he says returning a loan or returning a פיקדון. pikadon. Yeah
okay those were basically the cases. Fine.
Okay,
so where basically you have an obligation to give the money back
or a right to give the money back, there the other person
the definition of the act of giving might just be putting it
in the person's possession. Okay, let's take a look now at the
next משנה. mishna. That was a fun fun little episode discussion. Now
כל שהוא לפנים מן החומה kol shehu lifnim min hachoma back to
technical considerations of what's considered a house in a walled city.
Anything within the walls הרי הוא כבתי ערי חומה harei hu k'batei
arei choma is like a house in a walled city.
Doesn't have to be a house. Okay, כל שהוא, Kol shehu, meaning
it could be a store, it could be a storage facility. What
if it's a garden? What if it's not even a... what if
it doesn't even have four walls? So let's take a look. חוץ
מן השדות, chutz min hasadot, with the exception of fields. Okay, fields
are primarily things that are... you could have, I guess, in a
city, it's unlikely, but things that are used for growing wheat and
so on. A field isn't a house. But anything else is a
house. Now, of course, there are some things which are... which we'll
see in the גמרא, Gemara which aren't exactly fields, like for instance,
a tiny little vegetable garden or how about a flower patch? How
about a backyard? It's not meant for growing anything, but it has
no structure. Is that have the same הלכה halacha, as a house?
Okay, what is included in the category of a house? Okay, a
baseball field. Alright, so let's take a look. רבי מאיר אומר אף
השדות, Rabbi Meir omer af hasados, even fields. Now, בית הבנוי בחומה,
bayis habanuy bechomah, let's say you have a house in a wall.
Who had the famous house in the wall?
רחב. Rachav. We're going to quote her in a minute. So you
have a house in a wall. What's the question? So presumably the
issue is, is that your... is that it might be jutting out.
So you know, if you imagine the wall is flush on the
outside, but let's say, you know, let's say you look in apartment
buildings, right, you know, they've got a jutted out balcony. Let's say
you were had a jutted out portion of your house from the
wall. So is your house considered to be in the wall or
not in the wall? Or maybe even without jutting out, maybe the
very fact that one of the walls of your house is the
wall of the city, so the whole house is not within, part
of the house is the wall itself. So what's the הלכה? halacha.
So בית הבנוי בחומה, bayis habanuy bechomah, רבי יהודה אומר אינו כבתי
ערי חומה, Rabbi Yehuda omer eino ke'batei arei chomah, it does not
count. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, so רחב Rachav would have
sold for half, it would not have followed these laws. רבי שמעון
אומר כותלו החיצון היא חומתו, Rabbi Shimon omer kotlo hachitzon hi chomato,
no, the outer wall is your wall and it is the wall
of... it's both your outer wall and the wall of the city,
and it doesn't matter that it's doing double duty, it's still considered
like your house is within the city. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. בית. bayis, It says
if you have a house. אין לי אלא בית. Ein li ela
bayis. I only know a house. מניין לרבות בתי בדים, Minayin leravos
batei badim, how do I know the leather houses, ובתי מרחצאות, uvatei
merchatzos, the bathhouses, ומגדלות, umigdalos, the towers, like basically towers for like
a... whatever, like a... rooster, not... what a... pigeons or whatever.
שובכים. Shovachim. Whatever. שובכים Shovachim actually are like dove cotes. So מגדלות
migdalos is some other type of thing for birds. ובורות ושיחין ומערות,
uvoros veshichin ume'aros, and how about different types of wells? Now, this
is wells are interesting because they're all sort of have a sense
of man-made, but some actually have a structure and others basically... others,
you know, others are basically just dug holes in the... holes in
the ground. But other of them have like, you know, walls around
them and so on. But they all at least are to some
degree, you know, somehow man-made. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse says,
אשר בעיר, asher ba'ir, that is in the city. Anything in the
city. בית אשר בעיר. Bayis asher ba'ir. So יכול שאני מרבה אף
השדות, Yachol she'ani marbeh af hasados, maybe everything, even fields? תלמוד לומר
בית. Talmud lomar bayis. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. No, some...
somewhere between בית bayit. and אשר בעיר, asher ba'ir, it has to
be דומיה דבית, dumya de'bayis, similar to a house but not... but
not everything. Now again, what does that mean? Like I said, let's
say you imagine, I don't know, a baseball field. You know, it's
man-made in the sense that you needed to, you know, mow it
and whatever and shape it and whatever, but it's still fundamentally, you
know, just flat land, right? So at what point is it considered
not a שדה sadeh and it's considered in the בית bayit. category
is not exactly clear. Anyway, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says.
רבי מאיר אומר בית. Rabbi Meir omer bayis. אין לי אלא בית.
Ein li ela bayis. I only know a house. מניין לרבות בתי
בדים בתי מרחצאות מגדלות ושובכים ובורות ושיחין ומערות, Minayin leravos batei badim
batei merchatzos migdalos veshovachim uvoros veshichin ume'aros, ואפילו שדות? ve'afilu sados? How
do I know to include everything you said and fields? תלמוד לומר
אשר בעיר. Talmud lomar asher ba'ir. Anything in the city. והכתיב בית?
Vehachtiv bayis? Okay, so it says בית, bayis. seems to limit it.
אמר רב חסדא אמר רב קטינא, Amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Katina,
חולסית ומצולה איכא בינייהו. chulasit umetzulah ika beineiyhu. No, because there is
a difference about a חולסית chulasit and a מצולה. metzulah. מצולה Metzulah
is a swamp. A חולסית chulasit is, רש"י Rashi says that it's
basically, you know, just like some place that's completely unfit for planting.
Now, what is the issue there?
Meaning... meaning, ותניא, vetanya, well let's just read as we say in
a ברייתא, baraita, חולסית ומצולה, chulasit umetzulah, if you have this swamp
or this... place that cannot be planted, רבי מאיר אומר כבתים, Rabbi
Meir omer ke'batim, that's like your house, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
omer, and therefore it is... has the same הלכה, halacha רבי יהודה
אומר כשדות, Rabbi Yehuda omer kesados, it's like a field and it
does not have the הלכה. halacha So the way the גמרא reframes
the מחלוקת machlokes is that even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would agree
that something that is basically a field and made for planting is
not considered to be בית. bayis, So if you really have like
a wheat field, again I don't know how far that goes, let's
say it's a little vegetable patch in your backyard, you know, it's
not a big thing. But anyway, if you have something that basically
is ground that is planted, then or made for planting, everybody agrees
that's not בית. bayis What's the issue? The issue is something that
is fundamentally not man-made,
fundamentally ground, but it's also not a שדה. sadeh. Okay? So you've
got these things. You've got hard, you know, whatever, my baseball field
example, or even if it's not man-made, whatever, you have a hard
rocky field or you have a swamp. Nobody's planting anything in there,
okay, but so on the one hand it's not a שדה, sadeh,
but on the other hand it's not a בית. bayis So that
is what they're debating, but everybody would agree that something that is
completely different from a בית, bayis. which is the idea... planted field,
that is excluded. The question is this middle category. רש"י Rashi actually
tries to argue that even according to רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, the
reason that a swamp and this hard thing are considered בית is
because you could harvest some of the material from there to use
in the construction of a house. So he tries to make it
more like בית according to רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. I'm not sure
that's פשט. pshat. פשט pshat just might be that a שדה sadeh
is seen as the opposite of בית. Okay? And this type of
a thing falls between those two. It's not man-made. On the other
hand, it's not a שדה, sadeh, so how do you categorize it?
All right, so let's take a look at the next line. בית
הבנוי בחומה, Bayis habanui bachoma, רבי יהודה אומר אינו כבתי ערי חומה.
Rebbi Yehuda omer eino kevatei arei choma. Is it counted or not?
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. usheneihem mikra
echad darshu. They both interpreted the same פסוק. pasuk. ותורדם בחבל בעד
החלון, Vatoredem bachevel bead hachalon,
here's רחב, Rachav, she lowered the spies down with the rope by
the window. כי ביתה בקיר החומה ובחומה היא יושבת, Ki veitah bechir
hachoma uvachoma hi yoshavet, her house was in the wall of the
city and
she dwelt in the wall. רבי שמעון סבר, Rebbi Shimon savar, כפשטיה
דקרא, kepshatei dekra, the simple sense of the פסוק. passuk Her house
was within the wall, meaning she was considered to have a house
within the walled city even though it was built into the wall.
רבי יהודה סבר, Rebbi Yehuda savar, Rebbi Yehuda says it doesn't have
that status. He says, רבי יהודה סבר בחומה היא יושבת ולא בעיר
חומה. Rebbi Yehuda savar bechoma hi yoshavet velo be'ir choma. Yeah, she's
dwelling in the wall, but she's not dwelling within the walled city.
Okay, that's the whole point. To dwell within the walled city, your
whole house has to be inside of the wall. And here her
house is within the wall. So she's בחומה היא יושבת, bechoma hi
yoshavet, she's dwelling in the wall, but she's not dwelling בעיר חומה
be'ir choma in the city of the wall because that means that
it's actually she's not part of the wall itself. Okay, so that
is the house in the wall. Now we go to a definition
of what it means to be in a walled city.
But the whole story is that she's a resident.
Nobody is
denying the societal or sociological reality of that. There's a question about
whether halakhically, right, everybody agrees she's in the wall, she's a resident,
considered part of the city. The question is halakhically is she considered
to have a house in the walled city or not?
So where was the roof that she hid them?
I don't understand the question.
Well didn't she takes them up to the roof? Yeah. So would
the roof be the top of the wall? That would be stupid
because that would be visible.
Well, I actually had always imagined it that it was just that
it was sort of jutting out.
Yeah, that's what I thought. Right, on the inside of the wall.
Oh, your point is that she's not fully within the wall, she's
only partly within the wall. Yeah, okay, that's true. I don't think
the גמרא is claiming that she's fully within the wall. I think
it's claiming that halakhically she's considered to be living in the wall
and not in the walled city. Okay, anyway, let's take a look.
Now we go on to define what it means to be in
a walled city. עיר שגגותיה חומתה. Ir shegagoteha chomatah.
Let's say you have a city that its roofs are its wall.
Now it doesn't really literally mean roofs, it really means its walls,
the walls of the houses are its wall. Okay, so basically you
have a city that is all the houses are packed tight like
semi-detached houses all the way around and therefore the walls of the
houses form the wall. Now that's different from the previous question. We
could say if you've built a wall and then you built a
house in a wall, that's considered in the walled city. But here
the entire wall only exists as a
function of the walls of the houses. Is that considered a wall
or not? Not what the houses are considered, is the wall a
wall? ושאינה מוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון, Veshe'eina mukafet choma miymot
Yehoshua bin Nun, or let's say it has a wall but it's
not from the time of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua bin Nun. We're
getting close to פורים, Purim, everybody knows the importance of פורים Purim
about surrounded from a wall by the time of יהושע בן נון.
Yehoshua bin Nun. אינה כבתי ערי חומה, Eina kevatei arei choma, it
doesn't count. The wall has to be created as an independent entity
even if here or there a house is built into it, and
it has to be around from the time of יהושע בן נון.
Yehoshua bin Nun. Now that's interesting, we'll discuss why, but the simple
sense is, we can reflect later about the פורים Purim comparison, but
the simple sense is that the status if you assume that the
קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is defined by when they
went in at the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, not when they returned
in the time of עזרא, Ezra, then the status of these things
would be defined at the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. Is it considered
a walled city or not? Well, when did the status of ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael begin apply? From the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. Okay,
we will talk more about that in the גמרא, we will get
into the discussion about קדושה kedusha and so on. Okay, now, ואלו
הן בתי ערי חומה. Ve'elu hen batei arei choma. Here are they,
here are some of the cities. I'm sorry, well first here's some
of the description of what it means to be a city. שלוש
חצרות של שני בתים מוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון. Shalosh chatzerot
shel shenei batim mukafet choma miymot Yehoshua bin Nun. It's like a
little funny, because here's what's not, he says let me tell you
the criteria of what is. So here's what it is. So it
has to be surrounded with a wall from the time of יהושע
בן נון, Yehoshua bin Nun, that we already said, but it has
another criteria as well. The other criterion is that you have to
have at least three courtyards and in each courtyard two houses. I
mean we might call them streets. Okay, the way they had streets
was essentially courts, yards around which houses were built. So essentially you
need three streets and each street has to have two houses. Less
than that, it might be a village or it might be a
few houses, but it's not a city. To have the status of
a city, it needs to have at least three streets, two houses
per street. Where this comes from we'll see in the גמרא. Okay,
now, and here is a list of some of the... Examples of
cities like that, כגון, kegon, קצרא הישנה של ציפורי, Katzra Hayeshana shel
Tzipori, the old קצרא Katzra of ציפורי, Tzipori, there was a village
or whatever, a small little city near ציפורי Tzipori called קצרא, Katzra,
or the old one, וחקרא של גוש חלב, veChakra shel Gush Chalav,
and the city called חקרא Chakra of גוש חלב, Gush Chalav, ויודפת
הישנה, veYodfat Hayeshana, and the old יודפת, Yodfat, וגמלא וגדוד וחדיד ואונו
וירושלים, veGamla veGedud veChadid veOno viYerushalayim,
these are all cities that have walls from the time of יהושע
בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun and have at least, you know, three
streets and two houses per street, וכן כיוצא בהן, vechen kayotzei bahen,
anything like that. Which is interesting actually to have a very, you
know, reality type of a משנה Mishna listing actual cities. Now these
cities are by the way also mentioned in עזרא נחמיה Ezra Nechemya
when they, the cities that they inhabited when they returned. So you
can check it up there, I don't remember the exact פסוקים pesukim
off the top of my head.
It says כגון, kegon, that
implies that there are others as well.
But they gave at least one near יריחו. Yericho. Right, יריחו, Yericho,
right.
They're giving you some very practical examples, right. Now what are you
gaining by those practical examples? Why is the criteria sufficient? I don't
know. Maybe, maybe by these small ones to emphasize, yeah, it really
can be a very small city as long as it satisfies these
criteria. But again, it's not exactly clear, you know, other than maybe
it's just clarifying for you. You might not be aware that this
is מימות יהושע בן נון. mimot Yehoshua bin Nun. Or as we're
gonna see in the גמרא, even if it doesn't have a wall
now, as long as it originally had the wall. So you know,
there's reasons to try to establish what is on that list or
not. So let's take a look at the גמרא. תנו רבנן: Tanu
Rabbanan: חומה, Choma, a wall, ולא שור איגר, velo shur igar, not
a שור איגר shur igar is literally Aramaic for wall roof. Okay,
איגר igar is a roof, which is like what the משנה Mishna
said, עיר שגגותיה חומתה, ir shegagoteha chomata, that the roofs of the
houses are the wall. Again, it's funny that it uses the phrase
roof, but it's presumably doing that because it doesn't want to say
the walls are the wall, which would be confusing. But basically, it
has to be an independent wall, not that the homes of the
wall, not that the walls of the home create the wall. The
wall has to be independent.
סביב, Saviv, around it, פרט לטבריה שימה חומתה. perat leTverya sheyama chomata.
It excludes Tiberias where the ocean or whatever, you know, the, not
the ocean, but whatever, כנרת Kinneret serves as one of its walls.
So is it completely surrounded? Yes, but it's not completely surrounded by
a wall, one of it is Tiberias. Now by מגילה, Megilla, for
example, the גמרא asks what's the story of Tiberias? So although by
מגילה Megilla we normally make the comparison with the cases of מוקפת
חומה מימות יהושע בן נון, muketfet choma mimot Yehoshua bin Nun, and
this is the model for מגילה, Megilla, the גמרא actually says it's
not exactly the same, Tiberias might have a different status. Okay, we'll
talk more about מגילה Megilla a little bit later. רבי אלעזר ברבי
יוסי אומר: Rabbi Elazar berabbi Yossi omer: אשר לו חומה, asher lo
choma, that has a חומה, choma, but here the way it's written
is with a ו vav and an א. alef, I'll talk about
that in a minute.
Obviously the פשט pshat is that לו lo with a ו, vav,
that has a חומה, choma, but he's also reading it as לא
with an א, alef, that does not have a חומה. choma. What
does that tell you? אף על פי שאין לו עכשיו והיה לו
קודם לכן. af al pi she'ein lo achshav vehaya lo kodem lachen.
So it's the sort of, it's the full, you know, flip side
of the coin of a wall from the time of יהושע בן
נון. Yehoshua bin Nun. A more recent wall doesn't matter, and not
only that, if it had a wall in the time of יהושע
בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun and doesn't have now, its status is
still determined from the time of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua bin Nun.
And that also is a law by מגילה, Megilla, it doesn't matter
whether it has a wall now or not, it matters whether it
had the wall at the time of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua bin
Nun. Now it's interesting, what does that mean? What's the דרשה drasha
based on? So רש״י Rashi actually says that the word לו lo.
is written in the תורה Torah like this, a ו vav and
an א, alef, so it allows us to do the דרשה drasha
both ways. תוספות Tosafot says, what are you talking about? That's not
the way it's written in the תורה. Torah, So if you take
a look at this little תוספות, Tosafos אשר לו חומה, asher lo
choma, he says פירש רש״י לא כתיב, peresh Rashi lo ketiv, משמע
לו ומשמע לא, mashma lo umashma lo, with a ו vav and
an א, so you could read it both ways. It used to
have, but it doesn't have now. He says כלומר אין לו עכשיו
והיה לו קודם לכן. klomar ein lo achshav vehaya lo kodem lachen.
He says ואינו כן בחומשים מדויקים. ve'eino chen bechumashim meduyakim. It's not
true because in, you know, in
the precise חומשים, chumashim, כתיב לא באלף וקרי בוו. ketiv lo be'alef
vekari bevav. Okay, so meaning that תוספות Tosafot says that no, it's
not written לוא, lo, it's written לא, but we read it as
if it was לו. Now again, the pronunciation is the exact same.
So תוספות really says that the דרשה drasha is not based on
the way it's written, the דרשה drasha is just based on a,
on almost a מסורה masora that it has this sort of double
implication.
So that means that רש״י Rashi and תוספות had different texts.
Yeah, so there are times that
רש״י Rashi actually says, oh what does, why does this word have
an extra ו vav or an extra י? yod? And then תוספות
says we don't have an extra ו vav or an extra י.
yod. So רש״י Rashi actually sometimes had a text that was a
little bit off from the one that we have. I mean the
whole enterprise of the מסורה, masora, it's, you know, when did it
start?
Eighth century or so? Anyway, counting every single letter, trying to ensure
the precision of at least, you know, the text that we have,
but still there were variants. Okay, so let's take a look.
There's a גמרא that says we don't have an exact מסורה. masora.
Right, so but there was an attempt to try to make it,
to try to preserve what we did have
and, you know, to prevent future variations.
Yeah, I think that's what
תוספות says, right. תים קורבי מושב
עיר חומה... Tim Korbei Moshav Yerchoma... אשר לא... Asher lo... so actually
I wanted to check. So actually we have אשר לא חומה. Asher
lo choma. One minute, let me just check what this is.
לא קרי וכן בכל ספרים מדויקים כתיב באלף וקרי בואו. Lo krei
vechen bechol sefarim meduyakos ksiv be'alef u'krei bevav. וכן הכריע הר"ן... Vechen
hichria haRan...
anyway this person has a long note about the question about how
is it actually written. Okay, but yes, we have it written with
an אלף alef and we read it, what does it mean we
read it? It's pronounced the exact same, but we understand that the
meaning is with a ואו. vav. Okay, so anyway, let's keep on
going. ואלו הן בתי ערי חומה. Ve'elu hen batei arei choma. These
are the, these are they. תנא גמלא בגליל. Tana Gamla baGalil. So
the ברייתא baraita mentions more specifically where they're located.
גמלא Gamla in גליל, Galil, וגדוד בעבר ירדן וחדייד ואונו וירושלים ביהודה.
veGidud be'Ever Yarden veChadid veOno veYerushalayim biYehuda. מאי קאמר? Mai ka'amar? Why
does it have to be so specific of exactly where they're located?
And you could ask why does the משנה Mishnah bother mentioning them
at all, but okay, anyway, why being so specific? אמר אביי הכי
קאמר. Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar. This is what it's telling you. עד
גמלא בגליל. Ad Gamla baGalil. That only until you get to גמלא
Gamla in גליל, Galil, meaning presumably it depends which direction you're headed,
but presumably beyond גמלא Gamla within גליל Galil there are no more
walled cities.
עד גדוד בעבר ירדן וחדייד ואונו וירושלים ביהודה. Ad Gidud be'Ever Yarden
veChadid veOno veYerushalayim biYehuda. Okay, so maybe it's just saying there are
no more beyond that point. Again, it depends from where you're moving
to what say what beyond that point mean. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
רבא says maybe an easier explanation. גמלא בגליל, Gamla baGalil, no, only
the גמלא Gamla of גליל. Galil. לאפוקי גמלא דשאר ארצות. Le'apukei Gamla
de'sha'ar artzos. Meaning there might be other גמלאס, Gamlas, so the ברייתא
baraita is being precise, only the גמלא Gamla of גליל, Galil, not
other
גמלאס. Gamlas. גדוד בעבר ירדן. Gidud be'Ever Yarden. When I say גדוד,
Gidud, I mean the one in עבר ירדן. Ever Yarden. לאפוקי גדוד
דשאר ארצות. Le'apukei Gidud de'sha'ar artzos. Don't think I mean other
גדודס. Giduds. אינך דלא איכא דכוותייהו לא איצטריכא ליה. Inach delo ika
dechvasaihu lo itztrichlei. Okay, the
others that there were not other cities with those names or no
other city that you might have confused it with, they didn't have
to specifically identify the geographical location. But cities that had other cities
of the same name, right, you all know this, right, there are
plenty of cities, a lot of Alexandrias, there are a lot of
whatever, any Bethlehems. Okay, so those things you want to be more
precise which one you're referring to. Now we're going to switch gears.
בירושלים מי מחלטת? BiYerushalayim mi machlita?
Since when does the law of a בית בערי חומה bayis be'arei
choma apply to ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Right, that was listed. והתניא, Vehatanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, baraita, עשרה דברים נאמרו בירושלים. asara devarim ne'emru
biYerushalayim. There are ten things said about ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and one of
them is אין בית חלט בה. ein bayis chalat ba. The city
does not go, the house does not go over. Why not? Because
ירושלים Yerushalayim according to this is understood to be the possession of
all the tribes, it's like a capital
city, right, so it's an international, not an international, but a national
city. No one tribe has it particularly in their inheritance. And therefore
it's understood that the laws of בתי ערי חומה batei arei choma
only apply when it is considered to be basically a city that
is within a tribe's inheritance. Okay, but if it is not, then
it's completely excluded from these laws. Yes.
Uh-huh. There's these גמרות Gemaras that describe how exactly where the boundary
lines was in ירושלים Yerushalayim in the middle of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash
between יהודה Yehuda. and בנימין. Binyamin.
Right, so it's within, if you would, the region of יהודה, Yehuda,
but it's not possessed by יהודה. Yehuda.
Okay, and part of it was בנימין.
Right, that's true. So again, according to this, what that would have
to mean is it falls in their boundaries, but it's not possessed
by them. It remains possessed by all of the tribes equally, which
is a beautiful idea, right? So it says, and therefore, since the
whole idea is that the house is transferred permanently, the whole sense
of permanence, first of all, I start to say it as like
the whole law applies fundamentally when you begin with a שדה אחוזה.
sdei achuza. That's the way רש"י Rashi also says it, בית אחוזה,
bayis achuza, that how can you transfer it if you don't like
it's not really considered yours fundamentally yours. But you could also focus
on the person who begins with it, but the person who ends
with it, meaning to say that it's yours לדורותיו ledorosav suggests a
sense of permanence of your ownership, and at some fundamental level, you
know, nobody has permanent ownership in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I mean, obviously you
can own property, but at some fundamental level you can argue that,
you know, it always remains the at you know at the it
always remains owned by all of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. So anyway,
we understand that this is excluded. You don't own it enough to
transfer it fully or you can't own it fully, and therefore ירושלים
Yerushalayim is excluded from these laws. So how could we list ירושלים?
Yerushalayim? So rather than saying it's a debate, here's what we say.
אמר רבי יוחנן כירושלים דמוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan ki Yerushalayim demukafes choma miyemos Yehoshua bin Nun. No, we're using
ירושלים Yerushalayim as an example. It would have a wall, that would
have if any city like ירושלים Yerushalayim would have this law. ירושלים
Yerushalayim itself doesn't because special case, but anything like this, ולא כי
ירושלים, V'lo ki Yerushalayim, but not, it's not ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it doesn't
really apply to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. דאילו ירושלים אין בית חלוט בה. D'ilu
Yerushalayim ein bayis chalut bo. The whole laws don't apply because they
are not owned by a particular tribe, ואילו הכא הבית חלוט בהן.
v'ilu hacha habayis chalut bahen. Okay, and here it does, and in
other cases it would work. So ירושלים Yerushalayim is given as an
example, but it really doesn't apply to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which is always
dangerous to give an example of something that doesn't apply. So רב
אשי אמר, לאו אמר רבי יוסף, lav amar Rabi Yosef, I have
a better answer. רבי יוסף Rabi Yosef said in another context, תרי
קדש הוו. trei Kadesh havei. There are two Kadeshes, because when the
תורה Torah? talks about עד קדש ברנע ad Kadesh Barnea and קדש
Kadesh and whatever, there's problems in the פסוקים pesukim and he actually
says there's two places called קדש. Kadesh. Okay, so הכא נמי תרי
ירושלים הוו. hacha nami trei Yerushalayim havei. So maybe when the משנה
Mishnah says ירושלים Yerushalayim in יהודה, maybe there's another ירושלים Yerushalayim located
in יהודה. You'd think we might have known about that, but okay.
Anyway, it's a different ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Fine. Alright. תניא. Tanya. Now we
get to...
right, you should have the characteristics, right.
Now we get to the heart of I think this משנה, Mishnah,
which also ties us into, we'll touch on the issue about מגילה,
Megillah, which is the status of מימות יהושע בן נון. miyemos Yehoshua
bin Nun. Let's take a look. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua or רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי: Rabi
Yishmael b'Rabi Yosi: למה מנו חכמים את אלו? Lama manu chachamim es
elu? Why did the sages list these cities in the, in our
משנה Mishnah to tell me that they have the status of, you
know, of בתי ערי חומה? batei arei chomah? So he says, there's
a question exactly like what the context of this ברייתא braisa is,
but anyway, רש"י Rashi says that the context is those listed in
our משנה. Mishnah. So why were the cities listed in our משנה?
Mishnah? שכשעלו בני הגולה, Shekeshe'alu bnei hagolah, when those that returned from
the exile in the time of עזרא Ezra. came up, מצאו אלו
וקידשום, matzu elu v'kidshum, they found these
and they sanctified them to have the status of, you know, קדושת
ארץ ישראל kedushas Eretz Yisrael and the sanctity of cities of בתי
ערי חומה. batei arei chomah. אבל ראשונות, Aval rishonos, but the original
cities that were sanctified at the time of
יהושע, Yehoshua, בטלו משבטלה קדושת הארץ. batlu mishebatlah kedushas ha'aretz. They were,
their status was lost when the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed
the first time, which means according to him, it's not based on
יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua bin Nun. He's saying it's based on the
קדושה kedushah of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. If that קדושה kedushah needed
to be reinstated in the second בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so it's
only the things that had walls and were resanctified at the time
of the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And therefore it's only these
cities. All other cities, like maybe יריחו Yericho and other types of
things, if they weren't part of the second sanctification of the land,
they don't have their status. It's only things that were part of
the second sanctification of the land. Okay. קסבר, Kasavar, he is of
the opinion, קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה לעתיד לבוא, kedushah rishonah
kidshah l'sha'atah v'lo kidshah l'asid lavo, that the first sanctity of the
land was only for its time while there was a בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, but it did not last for forever. When the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed, it went away and it needed to
be resanctified in the time of the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
רמינהי, Remini, I'll ask you on this. אמר רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי,
Amar Rabi Yishmael b'Rabi Yosi, the same רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabi
Yishmael b'Rabi Yosi says the following in the following ברייתא: braisa: וכי
אלו בלבד היו? V'chi elu bilvad hayu?
It's basically starting with this list, but rather than saying, oh, only
this list because these were the only things of the second בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it takes the opposite tact. Why just mention these?
There were so many from the first בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. והכתיב,
V'haksiv, and lo, it is said, ולא כבר נאמר, v'lo kvar ne'emar,
it says in the תורה, ששים עיר כל חבל ארגוב כל אלה
ערים בצורות. shishim ir kol chevel Argov kol eleh arim betzuros. Right,
think about all the cities in עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. It says
there were sixty cities all surrounded by walls. So what do you
mean you mentioned a handful? So this is assuming that we go
by the first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or the first entry into
the land. So there's so many, why just mention these? So אלא
למה מנו חכמים את אלו? ela lama manu chachamim es elu? Why
did they list these? שכשעלו בני גולה, shekeshe'alu bnei golah, when they
came up in the time of עזרא, Ezra. מצאו אלו וקידשום, matzu
elu v'kidshum, they found these and they sanctified them. So what do
you mean? You just said before that it goes by the first
base, to the first time. So the גמרא interjects, קידשום, kidshum, sanctified
them? הא אמרת דלא צריכי לקידושינהו. ha amart d'lo tzrichi l'kidushineihu. You
just, you were just saying
that it all goes by the first time, it doesn't need to
be resanctified. אלא מנאום, Ela m'na'um, it doesn't mean sanctified, it means
when they came up they listed these. And then see how it
continues. ולא אלו בלבד, V'lo elu bilvad, now we're back to the
original quote, not only these that were listed, אלא כל שתעלה לך
מסורת בידך מאבותיך, ela kol sheta'aleh l'cha masores b'yadcha me'avosecha, anything that
you have a tradition going back to your forefathers, שמוקפת חומה מימות
יהושע בן נון, shemukefes chomah miyemos Yehoshua bin Nun, that was surrounded
with a wall from the time of יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua bin
Nun, כל מצוות הללו נוהגות בה, kol mitzvos halalu nohagos bah, all
of these laws of cities of surrounded with walls apply to it,
מפני שקדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא, mipnei shekedushah rishonah kidshah
l'sha'atah v'kidshah l'asid lavo, because the first sanctity was for, was for
all future times. So here actually you have two versions of רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabi Yishmael b'Rabi Yosi making the exact opposite assumption.
Right, why is this list so small? So one reason is because
it only goes by the second בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and it's
not by יהושע, Yehoshua, whatever, it all goes by the second. And
the other point is, these were just an examples, but really it
all goes by the first בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So which one
does he say? Doesn't he? So the גמרא says, אי בעית אימא,
ei bayis eima, if you want you could say, תרי תנאי אליבא
דרבי ישמעאל. trei tannai aliba d'Rabi Yishmael. So okay, you're right, there's
two versions of what רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael said, it's a debate
of תנאים tannaim what רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael said. ואי בעית אימא,
V'ei bayis eima, and if you want you could say, חד מינייהו
רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי אמרה. chad mineihu Rabi Elazar b'Rabi Yosi amrah.
One actually was a mistake in attribution, it wasn't רבי ישמעאל, Rabi
Yishmael, it was רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי. Rabi Elazar b'Rabi Yosi. Why
do we pick him of all people? Because we know that he
has a different we know what his position is about this debate.
דתניא DeTanya we taught in the ברייתא Baraita רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי
אומר Rabbi Eliezer Berabbi Yose Omer אשר לו חומה Asher Lo Homah
again this דרשה drasha of אשר לו חומה Asher Lo Homah אף
על פי שאין לו עכשיו והיה לו קודם לכן af al pi
she'ein lo achshav vehaya lo kodem lachen even if it doesn't have
a wall now as long as it had a wall before which
means that what period matters? What period matters is what it was
originally, what it was at the time of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua
bin Nun. Okay, so therefore what we so therefore that the one
that says you go from the time of יהושע Yehoshua clearly we
can associate it with רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Eliezer Berabbi Yose
and then the other one that says no you go by the
second קדושה kedusha the time of עזרא. Ezra? So here we have
right now this debate of whether you go by the first קדושה
kedusha or the second קדושה. kedusha. Now I want to take a
moment out to just step back and to assess why that matters
here. Okay, because normally what do we assume? We normally assume קדושה
kedusha
when I ask you do we go by the קדושה kedusha of
the first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
so on you normally the context of that conversation is for things
like תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros right? Do תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros apply
nowadays? If they do in which lands? In the lands that they
that they conquered at the time of יהושע Yehoshua the lands they
resettled at the time of עזרא. Ezra There's also another question if
you go by the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash how about how
much they possessed at the time of the חשמונאים? Chashmonaim? You know
how much does that continue? But still which do you go by
first or second? That's קדושה kedusha we normally talk about like if
you were the soil and the stuff that grows from the soil.
It's not so obvious I would have applied that to the status
of a house in a בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah right?
Which is not so much about the sort of קדושה kedusha of
the soil. You might say that it requires that the יובל be
practiced right? But why would it be right? Because obviously these are
laws of the יובל. But why would that but it's not as
obvious that it would be connected to the question of the קדושה
kedusha of the soil. From this גמרא it seems that it is.
It seems that it seems that you know because maybe of its
connection to the יובל if the if the land the soil is
קדוש kadosh from the time of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun
that defines the which cities are you know are בתי ערי חומה.
batei arei chomah. If that קדושה kedusha of the soil went off
then the status of בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah goes when
the קדושה kedusha of the soil is reinstated and again that could
be because of its connection to the laws of the יובל. But
that's one thing that's just to realize that it's a חידוש that
it's being connected to a concept of קדושה kedusha and I'm not
sure we would have necessarily assumed that. Now I want to add
another important point to that because what we often ignore it's a
tiny little משנה mishna somewhere and most people are are you know
I'm talking even people who've been learning in ישיבה yeshiva ten years
are oblivious to the fact although תוספות quotes it here that there's
another הלכה besides מגילה Megilla about בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah
about a ערי חומה arei chomah and that is the משנה mishna
in כלים Keilim that discusses different levels of קדושה kedusha of ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and there it's not talking about the soil because
there it talks about things like the קדושה kedusha of the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash the קדושה kedusha of הר הבית Har HaBayis so
it's talking about the place rather than of the soil. It says
that you know in the time when there was a משכן Mishkan
so you had the you had the מחנה שכינה machaneh shechina where
the משכן Mishkan was right? You had the מחנה לויה machaneh leviyah
where the לויים Levi'im were encamped around it and you had the
מחנה ישראל. machaneh Yisrael. Okay now the status of those things is
when you sent טמאי tamei people away the more טמא tamei you
are the further out of the camp you're sent and a מצורע
metzora is sent even out of מחנה ישראל. machaneh Yisrael. How did
that get translated to the reality in the land of Israel? So
מחנה שכינה machaneh shechina was the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. What was
מחנה לויה? machaneh leviyah? Anybody know? ירושלים? Yerushalayim? No. What's the next
stage? Yes the Temple Mount. The Temple Mount is מחנה לויה. machaneh
leviyah. What is מחנה ישראל? machaneh Yisrael? ירושלים Yerushalayim not all of
Israel. You don't send מצורעים metzora'im out of all of Israel right?
And when you read for example in תנ"ך Tanakh where were the
מצורעים? metzora'im? Remember שלושה מצורעים shlosha metzora'im where were they? Outside the
city. They were not outside of the land of Israel. So מחנה
ישראל machaneh Yisrael is ירושלים Yerushalayim but actually says the משנה mishna
in כלים Keilim not just ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Every walled city had a
status of מחנה ישראל. machaneh Yisrael. So therefore if you had a
מצורע metzora in a walled city you sent them outside the wall
right? They didn't they weren't out of ירושלים Yerushalayim they were out
of the wall. Even right right well if they were
in an unwalled city they could remain there because the status of
מחנה ישראל machaneh Yisrael which is interesting like to think conceptually that
that's a sense of sort of being contained protected somehow a more
you could be very far from ירושלים Yerushalayim because you would think
it had to do with relationship and proximity to the שכינה. shechina.
Anyway that is important that there's a general status of walled cities
of מחנה ישראל. machaneh Yisrael. So when it speaks about the second
קדושה kedusha and the first קדושה kedusha it might not just be
talking about the soil although normally that's what קדושה ראשונה ושנייה kedusha
rishona u'shniya is talking about is the soil but it might be
talking about the קדושה kedusha of the מקום makom of the place
and therefore the status of being this idea of מחנה ישראל machaneh
Yisrael and a special status of walled city which is not just
for this הלכה of יובל
of בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah that also might be dependent
on the first and second and also I'll say that that also
might be about why is it connected to מגילה? Megilla? Right? It's
bizarre that we connect right reading of the מגילה Megilla to
המוקפת חומה מימות יהושע בן נון hamukafes chomah mi'yemos Yehoshua bin Nun
and
whether it was קדושה ראשונה kedusha rishona קדושה שנייה kedusha shniya and
so on. Okay let's keep on looking a little bit more but
the first point is to just acknowledge that it's connected to the
sense of קדושה kedusha which is not necessarily what we might have
expected. So let's now see what the גמרא says.
מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה לעתיד לבוא?
Mai ta'ama deman de'amar kedusha rishona kidsha lish'ata velo kidsha le'atid lavo?
What's the reason of the person that says that it was only
for the time of יהושע Yehoshua but then it went away and
it had to be resanctified in the time of עזרא? Ezra דכתיב
the verse says ויעשו בני הגולה Vaya'asu benei hagola or כל הקהל
actually this פסוק passuk that תוספות quoted before כל הקהל השבים מן
השבי סוכות Kol hakkahal hashavim min hashvi sukkot they
celebrated the holiday of סוכות Sukkot when they returned to the land
of
ישראל. וישבו בסוכות כי לא עשו מימי יהושע בן נון Vayeshvu bassukkot
ki lo asu miymei Yehoshua bin Nun they never celebrated סוכות Sukkot
like this from the time of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun
כל כן בני ישראל. kol ken benei Yisrael. ותהי שמחה גדולה מאד
Vattehi simcha gedola me'od and it was a great joy. So now
the גמרא says what are you talking about? אפשר בא דוד ולא
עשו סוכות? Efshar ba David velo asu sukkot? What from the time
of יהושע Yehoshua they never did this? In the whole reign of
דוד המלך David Hamelech they didn't do a
סוכה sukkah until עזרא Ezra came this was the first time they
had a real celebration of סוכות? Sukkot? אלא Ella it can't really
mean that. So why does it connect it to יהושע? Yehoshua? מקיש
ביאתם בימי עזרא לביאתם בימי יהושע Makish bi'atam biymei Ezra livi'atam biymei
Yehoshua
to tell you that the returning they did in the time of
עזרא Ezra and you know in a way actually this might be
like a פשט pshat right because if you say what is the
power of connecting the סוכות Sukkot they kept in the time of
עזרא Ezra to יהושע בן נון? Yehoshua bin Nun? The power is
saying the message that it is like that they have now returned
to the land and we are evoking the reality of יהושע Yehoshua
saying we are returning to the land like when יהושע Yehoshua returned
to the land. Okay and therefore he's saying that actually has halachic
import. Okay so it says like
this אלא מקיש ביאתם בימי עזרא לביאתם בימי יהושע ella makish bi'atam
biymei Ezra livi'atam biymei Yehoshua the return in the time of עזרא
Ezra. to the return in the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. מה ביאתם
בימי יהושע מנו שמטין ויובלות וקידשו ערי חומה Mah bi'atam biymei Yehoshua
manu shmittin veyovelot vekidshu arei chomah the same way when they came
in the time of יהושע Yehoshua they had שמיטה they had יובל
they sanctified ערי חומה. arei chomah. Notice the phrase. It doesn't say
they sanctified the soil right? They sanctified the ערי חומה. arei chomah.
There's a status of ערי חומה. arei chomah. אף ביאתם בימי עזרא
Af bi'atam biymei Ezra when they returned in the time of עזרא
Ezra. same thing it was a reinstatement reinstating מנו שמטין ויובלות וקידשו
ערי חומה. manu shmittin veyovelot vekidshu arei chomah. ואומר Ve'omer oh walled
cities. Oh
what? ואומר Ve'omer and the verse says והביאך ה' אלהיך Vehevi'acha Hashem
Elokecha so that's the פסוק passuk. in נחמיה. Nechemya. Where do you
get it from the תורה? והביאך ה' אלהיך אל הארץ אשר ירשו
אבותיך וירשתה. Vehevi'acha Hashem Elokecha el ha'aretz asher yarshu avotecha viyrishtah. When
it talks about the wrapping up we were talking you know about
the after the תוכחה tochacha and after you're sent into exile it
says at the end of דברים Devarim God will return you to
the land that your fathers inherited and you will inherit. So you're
doing a new inheriting of the land when you return from the
exile. מקיש ירושתך לירושת אבותיך. Makish yerushat'cha liyrushat avotecha. Your inheriting is
like your fathers' inheriting. מה ירושת אבותיך Mah yerushat avotecha the same
way when they first came in and inherited the land בחידוש כל
הדברים הללו bechidush kol haddevarim hallalu they reinstated all these things. They
resanctified the land sanctified the walled cities שמיטה יובל. אף ירושתך בחידוש
כל
הדברים הללו. Af yerushat'cha bechidush kol haddevarim hallalu. Even when you inherited
it you reinstated. So that's for when they came in the second
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash says this approach everything had been lost the
slate had been wiped clean it was lost from the first time
and it was all reinstated in the time of עזרא. And therefore
why does the משנה Mishna mention just a handful? Because according to
this approach we just go by the time of עזרא. And there's
a special קדושה kedusha בתי ערי חומה. Battei Arei Chomah. Let's just
read one more sentence to see what the other approach does with
this פסוק. ואידך Ve'idach the other approach that says the קדושה kedusha
remained so why is it compared to the time of יהושע? Yehoshua?
דבעי רחמי על יצרא דעבודה זרה ובטליה. Deba'ei rachamei al yitzra de'avoda
zara uvatlei. Because there's a famous story that when they returned in
the time of the second בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash they said oh
my God the יצר הרע דעבודה זרה yetzer hara de'avoda zara this
is what caused the first בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash to be destroyed.
What are we going to do to prevent it? And they prayed
to God and God destroyed the יצר הרע דעבודה זרה yetzer hara
de'avoda zara which is a there's a famous מדרש Midrash and it's
a nice way of of transmitting the point that you know that
in the first בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash it's true they were Jews
were always running after עבודה זרה. avoda zara. In the second בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash there really wasn't such a יצר הרע yetzer hara
for עבודה זרה avoda zara anymore. You know the whole world reality
had changed. You know even the Romans that had all their pagan
gods it was much more like an outward type of sign. There
was not that that real passion that there used to be.
So anyway it's a fiery lion.
Yeah that's the story about the fiery lion. So this is why
it's compared to יהושע Yehoshua because דאגין זכותא עלייהו כסוכה. de'agin zchuta
aleihu kesukka. Because when it says the סוכות Sukkot it meant that
now that they they didn't have the יצר הרע yetzer hara they
were protected like they were under a
סוכה. sukkah. והיינו דקקפי קרי ליה יהושע. Vehainu dekakapi kari lei Yehoshua.
And that's why it's sort of being critical of יהושע Yehoshua דבכל
דוכתא כתיב יהושע devechol douchta ktiv Yehoshua with a ה hei והכא
כתיב vehacha ktiv in this verse that it said from the time
of יהושע Yehoshua it says ישוע Yeshua without a ה. hei. So
it's being a little critical. Why? Why is it critical? בשלמא *Bishlama*,
because why didn't יהושע *Yehoshua* do the same thing? If he would
have gotten rid of the יצר *yetzer* of עבודה זרה *avoda zara*
it would have saved the Jews a lot of צרות *tsuris*. So
בשלמא *Bishlama* משה לא בעי רחמי *Moshe lo ba rachamei*. I understand
why משה *Moshe* didn't try to get rid of the יצר הרע
*yetzer hara* דלא הוי זכותא דארץ ישראל *d'lo havei zechuta d'Eretz Yisrael*.
He wasn't in the land of ישראל *Yisrael*. Maybe he wasn't in
as good of a position to argue for it. אלא יהושע *Ela
Yehoshua* דהוה ליה זכותא דארץ ישראל *d'havei lei zechuta d'Eretz Yisrael*. He
has the merit. אמאי לא בעי רחמי *Amai lo ba rachamei*? Why
didn't he do what we did? He should have gotten rid of
the יצר הרע *yetzer hara* of עבודה זרה *avoda zara*. So therefore,
that's why it compares it to יהושע *Yehoshua* to say that to
be critical of יהושע *Yehoshua* that got rid of the יצר הרע
*yetzer hara* but not to say they reinstated. So here we have
the classic debate of whether the second when they came whether it's
the קדושה *kedusha* from יהושע *Yehoshua* or do they create a new
קדושה *kedusha*? And although normally that's a question about the soil and
תרומות ומעשרות *terumos u'maasros*, here it's more about the place, about שמיטה
*shmita*, יובל *yovel*, and about the status of בתי ערי חומה *batei
arei choma*. So just again to say how this ties into the
משנה *mishna*, the משנה *mishna* listed a handful and the question is,
is it only that handful because it all goes by the time
of יהושע *Yehoshua*? Or is it really a much, much larger... I
mean, because it's only that handful because it goes by the time
of עזרא *Ezra*? It's only the small numbers mentioned in the משנה
*mishna*. Or is it really that's just a representative list, but it
really is a huge list because it goes back to the time
of יהושע *Yehoshua* and that's what we are debating. We will continue
with this tomorrow.